<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discovery of theisme together with such philosophical and mathematical observations as are consonant thereunto : deliver'd in a more refin'd manner then hitherto written, against atheisme and prophaness / by a person of quality.</title>
            <author>Person of quality.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1660</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16081</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12952247</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12952247</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95951</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36132)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95951)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 735:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discovery of theisme together with such philosophical and mathematical observations as are consonant thereunto : deliver'd in a more refin'd manner then hitherto written, against atheisme and prophaness / by a person of quality.</title>
                  <author>Person of quality.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 94 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Charles Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95951:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95951:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOVERY OF THEISME.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER, With ſuch Philoſophical and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematical Obſervations, as are Conſonant thereunto: Deliver'd in a more refin'd Manner then hitherto Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, againſt <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> and <hi>Prophaneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>— Deum namque ire per omnes</l>
               <l>Terrarum tractuſque maris caelumque profundum.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Virgil.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Perſon of Quality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Charles Broome,</hi> at the <hi>Gun,</hi> at the Weſt-end of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:95951:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95951:2"/>
            <head>THE THEIST, TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>WHoſoever ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſe the Enſuing Treatiſe, will, I doubt not, to his Satisfaction, perceive that there is deliver'd in a more Excellent and refin'd manner ſuch Tenents as are genuinely appropriated to the ſublime Devotion of the Soul
<pb facs="tcp:95951:3"/>by the definition of <hi>Theiſme;</hi> and this perform'd in divers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable Inſtances and Proofs, that have not been the Subject of any precedent Pen. For tho it be granted that divers have Written on the Subject of <hi>Theiſme,</hi> yet the Method they have us'd in Publiſhing the Subſtance, in their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of that Perſwaſion, has been rather in the Nature of a Common-place, in every of their Writings, then duely Exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the manifeſt perſpicuity of that Doctrine as it is evident to the beſt Eye of Humane <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:95951:3"/>
            <p>And thus they would ſeem to apprehend that the <hi>Theiſt</hi> does rather ſuperſically Ruminate on the Notion and Being of a <hi>God,</hi> (tho viſibly convey'd to the Intellect by the ſublime Conduct of Providence together with the many wonderful Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtencies and Beings of things apparently diſcern'd in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe,) then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently adore the <hi>Deity</hi> in all thoſe conſiderations: As if miraculous Objects did not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitate the Reverence and Devotion of the Humane Soul, unleſs there be an Inadverten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Negligence by not Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically
<pb facs="tcp:95951:4"/>regarding the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction diſplay'd by the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty</hi> to every reaſonable Comprehenſion.</p>
            <p>He muſt be endu'd with a very Inſipid Senſe, that beholds a miraculous Structure without acknowledging an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Operator: And much more of a dimme diſcernment, if by the Fabrick of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe he did not conclude its Contex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture devinely Admirable: All which is ſo generally granted, that it has the validity of a proverbial Truth, on all ſides, rather then the leaſt Admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of Diſpute or Quere:
<pb facs="tcp:95951:4"/>But with this difference, that whereas others deduce, on the ſame account, their belief from words, which they conſider as Dictates from above, the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt</hi> derives his from the Works of the Omnipotent; ſo that there cannot be any Eſſential miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, in that Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, betwixt him, and any of his Oppoſers.</p>
            <p>If ſome Profeſſions of Faith undertake to define the Eſſence of the <hi>Deity</hi> more poſitively then is Conſiſtent with his Creed: (As they endeavour hy Sophiſticate Terms or Words of Art to exert the Infinite Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties
<pb facs="tcp:95951:5"/>and Being of the Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent, which cannot be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to the Humane <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding as it is converſant with Objects of Senſe, or things of a Corporeal Nature.)</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt</hi> does not deny, but in the Soul of Man there may be, in ſome reſpects, a very ſublime <hi>Idea</hi> of an unlimitted Capacity or extent, as from the moſt ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual part of Thought it has a momentary Progreſſion: And this is experimentally certain whenſoever the Imagination ſhall by an Inſtant Thought conceive a Geometrical Lime
<pb facs="tcp:95951:5"/>extended farther then all quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative Limitation in any kind: Much like that of <hi>Euclid,</hi> where he defines an Infinite line Incommenſurably reaching beyond all figurative Height, or Length; of which more at large in that part of this Treatiſe that relates to the Orbs above.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, if the Doctors of the Schools mean no other, by the Definition of the <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> however worded by them, then the moſt ſupereminent At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes of an Infinite Being, in all Capacities, there is no occaſion for controverting that Point betwixt the <hi>Theiſt</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:95951:6"/>them. Nor ought they to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, where it is Written, that <hi>God</hi> deliver'd himſelf to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> by no other Epithite then <hi>I am, what I am;</hi> which does not only poſe, but check Mortality that would under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to explicate the Divine Eſſence, beyond what is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to be comprehended by Mankind: Which the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent expreſſion of <hi>I am, what I am,</hi> ſo ſtupendouſly tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the utmoſt reach of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Senſe, does undeniably aſſure us. But of this ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blime Notion, more fully in the ſubſequent Treatiſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:95951:6"/>
            <p>Next to the Being of a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity,</hi> there ought to be a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend acknowledgement of the miraculous Import and Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence in the Conduct of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence, which in the Judgment of the <hi>Theiſt,</hi> is conſpicuouſly diſcernable in the Whole, and every Part of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe; and ſo very appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that it does by its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Viſibility avert the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate Man from having his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding diverſly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex'd, or envelop'd by the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity of Traditional or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated Miracles, of which he can have no ſenſible proſpect:
<pb facs="tcp:95951:7"/>As may be compendiouſly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by peruſing this Book; where not only the actual Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Providence are treated more applicably Intelligible, then has as yet been obſerv'd in the Writtings of others. But alſo ſome things of high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, or not before diſcover'd, no leſs manifeſtly prov'd by Mathematical certainty: Yet ſo perform'd, that it is made ſenſibly demonſtrative to any Reader who is not experienc'd in that Science. Some there are that Ignorantly enough un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to accuſe <hi>Theiſme,</hi> as if it oppoſs'd all Reveall'd
<pb facs="tcp:95951:7"/>Worſhip: Notwithſtanding that the External Convictions of Providence are inſeparable from his Belief; but this Reflection, as the <hi>Theiſt</hi> apprehends, does proceed from ſuch who contend more for the Credit of the Intricacy of their Doctrines, or Metaphyſical Diſtinctions, then the open Motives of Faith, that ought to Illuminate their Conceptsons: From whence it is very Remarkable, that Men Bigotted by Imaginary Notions, or accuſtom'd to a careleſs and ſloathful Regard of the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Convictions expoſs'd by the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty</hi> in the Wonders of his Works, do live, as if they diſeern'd not, or were ſurfeited with the continual Bleſſings that Providence, the great Leiutenant of the <hi>Deity,</hi> beſtows, as Comforts to their Souls and Bodies, by Day and Night upon them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:95951:8"/>
            <p>Others there are, tho agreeing with the <hi>Theiſt</hi> in their Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging and Worſhiping of a ſole <hi>Deity:</hi> Yet are ſeverely Imbitter'd againſt him, becauſe he does not tack to his Belief ſuch a Catalogue of Articles of Faith, as each of them profeſs annex'd to their Creed.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer to which, the <hi>Theiſt</hi> deſires them to Conſider, that they are ſo far from accomodating, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt themſelves their different Manner of Worſhips, together with divers eſſential Particulars by which they depart farther from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they can pretend to do from the Doctrine of <hi>Theiſme:</hi> As is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preceptible in the <hi>Jew, Meho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metan,</hi> and other perverſe Beliefs: Yet all of them Concenter with the <hi>Theiſt</hi> in the Adoration of one ſole <hi>God:</hi> Which enough does manifeſt that the Belief of one <hi>God</hi> is the
<pb facs="tcp:95951:8"/>moſt demonſtrative Article of their ſeveral Perſwaſions: As alſo that their Diſſentments, Enmities, and violent Oppoſitions, in Reference to the uncertainties of other of their Tenants, even to the Subvertimg of Civil Repoſe, and Government, may be Recorded amongſt the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Calamities of Mankind.</p>
            <p>But on theſe ſad Accounts, ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly known, the <hi>Theiſt</hi> is more modeſt then to Inſert his Recrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</p>
            <p>And thus in Brief, are here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, by way of Preface, ſuch Sentiments of the <hi>Theiſt</hi> as prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively Conduce to the facilitating of the Readers Apprehenſion of the enſuing Work: Which is chiefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd againſt the abſur'd Impieties of <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> with a due Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on ſuch that diſregard, in Soul, the Miracles of the <hi>Almighty</hi> as
<pb facs="tcp:95951:9"/>ſo many Innumerable Bleſſings, throughout the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe convey'd, for the benefit of Mankind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To Conclude, the</hi> Reader <hi>is deſir'd to take Notice, that there is nothing Intended, in this</hi> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, <hi>whereby to Leſſen in any kind, the Excellencies of</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, <hi>but rather an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of its Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, as may be evidently perceiv'd in the Cloſe of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Book.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95951:9"/>
            <head>A DISCOVERY Of the moſt Refin'd NOTIONS and PRINCIPLES Of the THEIST. As they Eſſentially Relate to that PERSWASION.</head>
            <p>THE Religion of the <hi>Theiſt,</hi> as the Word may be deriv'd from <hi>Greek,</hi> Conſiſts in the ſole belief of one God, with all other Attributes of miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Being, Providence, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95951:10"/>that can be aſſign'd to Omnipotency. In which gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Article of Divine Belief, the <hi>Theiſt</hi> fully concenters with the moſt Univerſal Religions of the World: But in the motives to Divine Worſhip, he conſiderably differs from many of them, which may be thus explain'd: The <hi>Theiſt</hi> derives his Adoration of a Deity, from the Being and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Order of the Univerſe in the Exiſtency of the World above, and below, with what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is contain'd therein, which ſumm'd compleats the Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God demonſtrated by the wonders of his Works, which he believes ought undeniably to oblige the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Holy reverence of the Soul as the moſt viſible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions of his Creed: Or no other then ſo many Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95951:10"/>in the miraculous operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and conſiſtency of the World ſenſibly apprehended by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable conduct of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. If he beholds the miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Revolution above, together with the riſing and ſetting of the Sun to day, he thinks it no leſs ſtupendious if he perceives his Glorious Aſcent to morrow: And thus he fits his belief to the Volume of Divine Faith com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in the Worlds univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Continuance and Being, as ſo many Evidences of the Deity convey'd by Incomprehenſible Cauſes and Effects. In which ſubmiſſion of the Soul, he cannot but ſeperate his Holy contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and reverence from other Credentials of Worſhip that are written, or diſperſs'd by the Hand of Man, as he that has an
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95951:11"/>open aſſurance, need not uncloſe a Book to ſearch for more; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a writing however credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly aſſerting the Truth of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles paſt, which celebrate parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Worſhips, cannot as he Judgeth, be ſo preſent with his Underſtanding, or his Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Conviction, as what is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual to his Apprehenſion, in the miraculous Conſtitution, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, and Providential ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the Univerſal World, with the innumerable Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Admiration contain'd in it, that does, as it were, diſcloſe to the Eye the boſome of Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potence; in which the devout preception of Man may diſcern dateleſs Miracles no leſs Antient in Being then the total World; becauſe always evident in it. Whereas contrarily, in the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95951:11"/>of the <hi>Theiſt,</hi> other Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perſwaſions want not only the like continual manifeſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions; but according to the known Date of their Records, muſt acknowledge that there was, for ought they can demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratively alledge to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, innumerable Years that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the Revelations they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert: From whence may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded that there was unaccoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Revolutions of Time when they neither had Being or Belief. And therefore no Objection, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Theiſt,</hi> if he rejects Tenents that include a Modern Date; or not ſo Infinitely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>computable by Time, as his own: It being impoſſible to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence any Conviction of the Soul more Antient than the World, and the Miracles it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95951:12"/>Not but the Divine Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er could have ordain'd, if ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his Decree, one or more ſubſequent Worlds as amply wonderful as this we behold; there being no limitation to the Omnipotent, if pleas'd to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow any miraculous Method in order to our Senſe and Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But then this muſt have been perpetually evident from the time it had Beginning, as clearly as is diſcernable any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Object of Divine Admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Reverence within the compaſs of the Univerſe. On which conſiderations, the <hi>Theiſt</hi> conceives himſelf obliged to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from divers miraculous Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents deliver'd by the Pens of men, becauſe not genuinely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcernable in the vaſt Volume of the World, without any inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95951:12"/>of Wonders, and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence conſonant to their Divine conveyance. It being a Sole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciſme, in his opinion, that men ſhould recede from the day light of Faith, to ſearch for Inviſible Conviction. And conſequently Inferrs, that ſince there are no apparent Miracles, but what are contain'd in the Univerſe of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, he ought to prove from thence the devotion of his Faith. On which account he amply receives the aſſurance of Divine demonſtration by the Eye of his Intellect: Leaving o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Creeds to argue, from tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions of ſpiritual Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, their Syſtems of belief; or from whence they ſeverally In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr, as they rationally gather, that the Holy Precepts, of one or other, are to be embrac'd by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95951:13"/>them. Whereas, the greateſt part of religious Perſwaſion are rather the Effects of Cuſtome and Education, then viſible Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of any faculty of the Humane Soul.</p>
            <p>Inſomuch, that the <hi>Theiſt</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, that a Man born blind, may be as Intelligibly perſwaded of the Doctrine of <hi>Theiſme,</hi> together with the devotion an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to it, as if he had a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſight and proſpect of all the Wonders within the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of the Univerſe. It not being to be doubted that ſuch a perſon, tho without Eyes to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern, might by his Reaſon, or Senſe of Feeling, not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that he lives, but that he is alſo ſuſtain'd by a providential Goodneſs and Power, as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly as he feels within, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95951:13"/>out him; the Effects of Heat or Cold, as alſo nouriſh'd by Food, neither of which could be produc'd or caus'd by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; And therefore muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede that he Subſiſts by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation of an Exiſtence more excellent then his own; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently oblig'd to give thanks devoutly on his knees for the Bleſſings he receives, tho with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Eyes to behold the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of Heaven and Earth, from whence they proceed.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, ſhould this unſeeing Man be requir'd to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to any religious Propoſal, that preſented no other contex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to his Senſe, then a ſtory told of ſuppernatural Deeds and Revelation, which concenter'd with no Rational Proprietic of his Being and Nature: He would
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95951:14"/>doubtleſs Annex his belief to the Doctrine of <hi>Theiſme,</hi> with what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, by undeniable conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence from it, might compleat his Devotion. Theſe diſcuſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as being but previouſly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted in order to farther ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pand the Fonds on which the <hi>Theiſt</hi> erects his Tenents; It will be neceſſary to conſider theſe three Particulars.</p>
            <div type="particulars">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:95951:14"/>
               <head>The <hi>Firſt,</hi> As to the Being of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe. The <hi>Second,</hi> Tending to the Cauſe and Manner of its Productiony, as alſo its won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Conduct, Order, and Preſervation, with ſome Opinions of the Learned The <hi>Third,</hi> Including the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the <hi>Theiſt,</hi> and the manner of Holy Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion redounding from thence.</head>
               <div n="1" type="particular">
                  <head>As to the Firſt Particular.</head>
                  <p>THE <hi>Theiſt</hi> does not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern his Imagination with the trite conteſts that both amuſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95951:15"/>and weary Mens underſtandings, by their Impoſſible determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as they are Debated in Schools; where ſome undertake to determine that, by the Effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Divine Will, the World had an original Creation from nothing: Or as others Aſſert, from matter that had a precedent Exiſtency, and afterwards di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpos'd by Omnipotency into the Figure we now behold. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which opinions the <hi>Theiſt</hi> allows to be his: It being more perſpicuous, in his Judgment, to believe that the Univerſe, with all it contains, is admirable, then to define by what Method, or Means its wonderful Structure was produc'd. But however it came to paſs, 'twas certainly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh'd, without pains, by whatſoever was the manner of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95951:15"/>the operation, becauſe in every thing it comprehends there is an eaſineſs of Order and Being; otherwiſe there could be no one Individual, of any kind, but might be deſtructive to another, and the Cauſe periſh with the Effect, which would tend to a period of Providence.</p>
                  <p>Fox tho it be apparent that Bodies of Life, whether Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, or Vegetables, are ſubject to alteration and Death as any of them corupt in order to the Generation of others, yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is abſolutely deſtroy'd, but rather varied as a continual ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement to more productions; ſo that the Cauſe remains entire, however it effects Alteration.</p>
                  <p>Examples are obvious, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Particulars, of which, theſe are ocularly Illuſtrious; the Sun,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95951:16"/>Moon and Stars, are influential Cauſes of innumerable Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Bodies beneath 'em, yet have no change in themſelves, as they Operate on other things. And thus it is very manifeſt that the vaſt Bulk of the Univerſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts by open providential Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and their Effects, which by a Series of humane Thought, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend untill the Imagination, to wonder leaves 'em, as being not within its Capacity to proceed higher: And therefore, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the poetical, Alluſion of <hi>Homer</hi>'s Chain of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſtupendiouſly Comits the Scals of its Cauſes, as fixt at the foot of <hi>Jupiters</hi> Chair.</p>
                  <p>If the total complexe of the Univerſe, does admirably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict us that it has an unconceiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Structure and Being, the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95951:16"/>Author of its Exiſtency muſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe on the Soul a more ſublime Admiration, which by the <hi>Theiſt</hi> is readily devoted to Divine Omnipotency.</p>
                  <p>There is no ordinary Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that may not Signally perceive the providential Reſults in Cauſes and Effects, of a deifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Power; but not with the ſame poſſibility diſcern the Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Eſſence of the wonderful Author.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding, it is obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly apparent, that there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities of Elementary Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Subſiſtencies appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Earth, on which we tread, that, as to the Cauſes from whence they proceed, are as far remote from our Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as any Influenc'd from the ſupreameſt Orb of Heaven:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95951:17"/>Which experience fully aſſures, it being not more obſcure to our Intellects, why ſome parts of Earth ſhould encloſe divers Materials, Mines of Diamonds, Gold, Silver, Minerals, Streams, and watry Depths, when in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are found Quarries of Stone, and Impenetrable Rocks.</p>
                  <p>Nor leſs clouded will be our Imagination, ſhould we ſearch on Mountains tops, and then diſcover the Head of a Spring, that by ſecret deſcending ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies perpetually the Current of a mighty River: Would not a Man think that it were as Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to think the Cauſe of this wondrous Scource, as by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to conceive why the Boſome of the Earth ſhould nouriſh the different Materials already men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd. Yet duely conſider'd,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95951:17"/>the Uſes for which they are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the courſe Stone or Pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble differs not in Value from the pureſt Diamond, as being more frequent for uſage, tho not, in opinion, of the ſame price: So variouſly has Providence provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for our Ornaments and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies of Life. Could the Univerſe be compair'd with any Conception of the Humane Mind; it were poſſible to Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine a World as prodigiouſly wonderful, in Whole and in Parts, as this we viſibly behold; but that were to extend thought beyond what is actually Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and therefore no leſs Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd then Impoſſible; becauſe we could think of nothing but would have ſome material Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, to what was obſerv'd before, within the Compaſs of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95951:18"/>the World we Inhabit: On which Ground it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded that there can be no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle to Senſe, either great or ſmall, other then what is locally Encompaſs'd by the Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Heaven and Earth.</p>
                  <p>Should a Man endeavour, by any Extaſie of Thought, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the Being of Deity, his Imagination could extend no farther then the uſual Courſe of providential Operations: And ſhould he attempt to explain the Divine Eſſence, he could not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate his thought from Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the Corporeal Shape and Likeneſs of ſome Object he had before obſerv'd. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, 'tis a preſumption in words, if deliver'd by them, that God can be otherwiſe underſtood then by his admir'd Providence and Works.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:95951:18"/>
                  <p>Nor is it poſſible to Attribute other Definition to Omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; for tho God may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to have the utmoſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of ſpiritual Exiſtency, and what is more, demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively ſuch by operations of a ſpiritual Nature, or equivalent to it, as ſhall be evidently prov'd in the next Particular of this Treatiſe: Notwithſtanding, it ſeems Impoſſible to word the Definition of a Spirit, becauſe nothing can be deliver'd by Speech but muſt be the Object of one, or more, of the Senſes, and no Man will averr that he can either ſee or feel a Spirit: It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unconceivable that a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal Eye or Senſe whatſoever, ſhould perceive any thing that has not bodily parts; otherwiſe then it may be exerted in ſome
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95951:19"/>equivalent Capacity, as already expreſs'd.</p>
                  <p>But before the firſt Grand Particular, of this Treatiſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives a period: The <hi>Theiſt</hi> would be underſtood that where he mentions the miraculous Sru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture and Continuance of the total Univerſe, he does not An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex a more Ineffable Wonder to the Whole then he does to every individual Part, whether of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimal or Vegetable Subſiſtency. A Miracle is as abſolute in Epitomy as in the utmoſt extent of Bredth, Depth, and Height: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that every particular thing appertaining to Earth, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove and below its Surface, are no leſs ſtupendious then the vaſtneſs of its Circumference and Bulk.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:95951:19"/>
                  <p>If ask'd why the Earth is adorn'd with Flowers of a various Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and Beauty, and but the Graſs and Leaves of Trees green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly flouriſhing: The moſt intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legent Man can give no perfect reaſon, no more then if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd to prove why any one Stone appears of a comlier Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure and Complexion than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If farther demanded how Rivers and Seas are ſupply'd with numberleſs Streams that are maintain'd and encreas'd: He muſt profeſs his Ignorance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe unknown to him, both the manner of the Operation and Materials by which they were originally produc'd. If intero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated why Air is thiner then Earth or Water, or why Stars are brighter then Trees, or not obſerv'd to augment by growth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95951:20"/>like them, he muſt for the ſame Reaſon, anſwer as ignorantly as he did to any of the precedent Queſtions.</p>
                  <p>To conclude, had it pleas'd Omnipotency to have beſtow'd rational Underſtanding to every Species of Being, and Life in the Regions of Air and Earth toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with whatſoever has a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid Exiſtence in the Streams and Oceans of the Univerſe: The Fiſh, Beaſt, and Plant, would no leſs admire the diverſities of their Nature's Proprieties, and Shapes, then thoſe of Man and Woman, or how all of them Subſiſt and Encreaſe in their ſeveral kinds. Neither could Mankind leſs ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiouſly wonder how any of thoſe were produc'd, then by what means the firſt Man and Woman had a primitive Life:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95951:20"/>In which conſideration, the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Intellect is no leſs pos'd by the Miracle of its own Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Being, then it is by contemplating how the vaſt Sructure of the World, with its ſumm of Wonders, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated as 'tis now beheld.</p>
                  <p>Which prefectly demonſtrates that there is neither <hi>magis,</hi> or <hi>minus,</hi> in the miraculous Act whereby was produc'd the total Univerſe, or any Individial thing that is contain'd by its Icommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable Compaſs.</p>
                  <p>From whence the <hi>Theiſt</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes that Omnipotency may be Emphatically defin'd by the Miracles of its Works, ſince by no other Definition, or Sylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme, which the Schools pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide, it can be ſo viſibly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended.</p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:95951:21"/>
                  <p>And it were vain to Imagine that the Divine Power, too In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite to be comprehended by any Syſtem of words, ſhould be by that Method, no leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victive, to the Eye of Thought, then it is by ocular demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Things manifeſtly Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: Wherefore Mankind ought to acknowledge, with the higheſt Reverence of the Soul, that the Eſſence of Omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Imcomprehenſible by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents of Speech, may be equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently explain'd in the ſuperlative Wonders of the World, and the Works it contains. Which in ſumm, is the Doctrine of the <hi>Theiſt,</hi> as it relates to a Divine Power and Being,</p>
                  <p>But as to the Sphere or Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Almighty; which by the Tenents of ſome is Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95951:21"/>to be above the Supreameſt of the Celeſtial Orbs, the <hi>Theiſt</hi> does not undertake to define; which were no leſs abſur'd then to attribute to an Infinite a circurnſcrib'd Being.</p>
                  <p>The Geometrician certainly proves, that nothing can be ſaid to have place; other then what is contain'd by proportional Lines within the Compaſs of ſome Figure: Whereby he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrates, that whatſoever is alledg'd to proportion, muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently be allow'd Parts, as in the Dimention of Alineal ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies, in any kind, or ſolids, as the Cube, Globe, Cone, Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bola, or the like: The moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent of which cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the Figure of Deity, which if without Body, there is no poſſibility of its reſemblance to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95951:22"/>any Corporeal Thing or Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: Wherefore the denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Heaven, tho Immenſly ſuppos'd beyond the higheſt of Stars that ſhine to wonder above us, is too narrow a Station for the Prefence-Chamber of the Deity: Becauſe the nominating of Place does imply the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of material Parts; and no Man can be ſo Ignorant as to ſuppoſe that there is any ſuch thing as a bodily Infinite, or that any local quantity may be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comenſurably acknowledg'd.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding it muſt be granted that the opinion of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Perſons, tho not ſtrictly to be prov'd, in appropriating to the ſublimeſt height the manſion of Omnipotency, is allowable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe devout contemplation the farther it aſcends upward has a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95951:22"/>more remote, or ineffable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, as being exalted above Things of more familiar obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, tho not leſs Admirable; as has been precedently obſerv'd, then conſiſts in the ſpeculation of any heigher objects of thought that impreſſeth on the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, Reverential acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of a Supream Power that by its munificence ſupports the Fabrick of the Univerſe, and all it contains: Wherefore, in Reverence to diſcernleſs or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Being, a place unknown, as the moſt ſuitable Epithite, may be term'd the ſelect Seat of the Almighty. The Nature of Men having more dread, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, unperceptible of what they conceive they ought ſtupendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to believe then if it were preſent to their Underſtandings:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95951:23"/>Inſomuch that could the humane Eye ſurpaſs its uſual proſpect of the Sun and Stars, and next make a viſible diſcovery of a Heaven far more Glorious then any of the ſhining Sphere alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy diſcern'd, the wonderful Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects might, in ſhort time, be as regardleſly perceiv'd as any of the ſublime Illuminations ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd before.</p>
                  <p>So heedleſs is Man of things that require his perfect Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
                  <p>But as to the denomination of Heaven, as a ſublime ſome where, rather then place of the Bleſs'd, as the Schools define, with the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical Viſion of the Almighty, as alſo the perpetual Felicity of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Immortality: 'Tis a paſſible Opinion in the Judgment of the <hi>Theiſt,</hi> and may not be Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruouſly
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95951:23"/>deriv'd from experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Obſervation; as by the Eye the Imagination aſcends by comparing the different Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, Heights, and Splendors of the Moon, Sun, Planets, and Stars; by which gradual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, or as it were ſtep, by ſtep, is apprehended a more Divine and ſublime Being of the Deity.</p>
                  <p>The great Philoſopher <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> was not diſſentaneous to this Notion, when he defin'd the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial appearances, ſo term'd here inſtead of Bodies, for Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that will ſoon follow, by the Name of a fifth Eſſence, as an extraordinary refin'dneſs In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to their Being and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Invariable in their Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure and Figures without the leaſt ſignification or tendency
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95951:24"/>to Elementary Compoſition or Change, as ſo many particular Emblems of Eternity, by whoſe admir'd Illuminations the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Soul might be guided to the tranſcendent acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a more Illuſtrious and Divine Exiſtence.</p>
                  <p>But enough has been ſaid rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the firſt Branch of this Treatiſe, and the Being of a God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="particular">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:95951:24"/>
                  <head>The <hi>Second</hi> Particular, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Cauſe and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Worlds producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: As alſo its wonderful Conduct, Order, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; with ſome Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Learned therein.</head>
                  <p>IT has been evidently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd, by the precedent Diſcuſſions, that the Univerſe, withall its ſurrounds, is diſplay'd as ocularly miraculous: And therefore incumbent on humane Senſe to be a diligent Admirer of all its Objects. The neglect of which cannot be enough Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd, ſince it proceeds from
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95951:25"/>ſloathful Imprudence, or Inad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertency of Men, in being not more propenſly diligent in devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Duty of their admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations as fully as the Wonders of Providence are obvious to their ſight Inſomuch, that a tale told of any extraordinary Fact, if but ſuppos'd miraculous, ſhall more aſſure their Imaginations, then what may be Admirably beheld in the open Face of the Univerſe, every minute of Life Or that familiar Convictions, becauſe familiar, ſhould be leſs regarded then ſtupendious Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions without ocular or ſenſible Aſſurance: Whereas the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful continuance of Objects, and ſuch are thoſe which are perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly numerous, and within the Compaſs of the World, ought to Induce our moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95951:25"/>and ſolemn Admiration as ſo many teſtimonials of an Omnipotent Author. Not that the <hi>Theiſt</hi> would occaſion, by Aſſertions of this Nature, ſuch perplexities in the Soul as are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd in Men that would under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to diſcover Cauſes and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects far obſcur'd by the Vail of Providence; or by what me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of Omnipotency the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe had Original Beginning. The moſt general belief of Men, however differing in other Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents, either as they are <hi>Jews, Chriſtians,</hi> or <hi>Mahomitans,</hi> Is, that the total World together with all it circumſcribs above and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, was by the Will and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate of the Almighty created from nothing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And that Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal Subſtances, defined by the Schools: Angels and Spirits had
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95951:26"/>a concometant production with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſs of ſix Days, as the Scripture affirms, with Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Bodies of innumerable Kinds according to the diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of their Scituations, Shapes, and manner of Subſiſtence.</p>
                  <p>But here it muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that it cannot be proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Imagin'd how an Infinite Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Operator ſhould be ſaid to effect, in any degrees of Time, whatſoever was produc'd by Omnipotent Power; becauſe every Act that may be compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or number'd in Time, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſwift its Accelaration pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth Motion and Comenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Parts, which were too hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily attributed to the Method and Deeds of the Almighty. Wherefore the expreſſions may rather paſs for a manner of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95951:26"/>whereby Holy Writ would more familiarly captivate hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Underſtanding, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not apprehend or think of any Object or Exiſtency, in any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, that is not, more or leſs, within the Verge of Time as it is judg'd by the Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. So that where the Text enumerat's Days in which the Univerſe was compleated; 'tis not meant as if God had ſet a task upon himſelf, to be finiſh'd in any Journals of time, becauſe the Effect of his Eternal Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination could have no tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary Epithite; and therefore the words of the Writer whereby to deliver, for the benefit of humane Capacity, the Infinite Decree and Operations of the Omnipotent, as temporarily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd; muſt be ſo intended, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95951:27"/>impoſſible to be apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in any other dialect, and Man the Reader.</p>
                  <p>Another Opinion the <hi>Theiſt</hi> obſerves, and much affected by modern Authors; which is, that there was a material World in Being before it had the Date of Creation from the Pen of <hi>Moſes:</hi> Affirming, according to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Maxim, that of nothing, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be made; and this original Matter, tho by them ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſs'd Corporeal, had no perfect compoſition till diſpoſs'd by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence into ſuch bodily Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions and Forms as are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in the ſupreamer and lower Regions of the Univerſe. In this Chaos of Matter, in conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to their Syſtem of the Worlds Production, muſt unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably be granted a capacitative
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:95951:27"/>Being of Incorporeal Subſtances, as well as thoſe that appertain'd, as they Affirm, to the bulk of Matter, and by the ſame proceſs receiv'd a future perfection: By which Conception of theirs they ſeem, abſurdly to complicate Eternity of Matter, and Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of all Kinds, whether Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real of Spiritual; untill all of them were ſubſequently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated by Divine Ordination: but this Imagination tends not only to Aſſert a double Eternity, by allowing a perpetual Exiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to Matter, as well as to the Being of an Omnipotent Power, but alſo by affirming that all thnigs were previouſly diſpoſs'd, from ſomething, either Corpore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al or Spiritual, that was Incedent to their precedent Capacities; by which they annex a tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95951:28"/>Operation to the Works of the Almighty. So that, in effect, they allow, inſtead of Creation, no other then a providential Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration and Refinement of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Parts, no leſs then Subſtances, that were to be exalted to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Perfection. From which modalities, or manner of prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and future Subſiſtences, they derive their Tenents relating to the Being of Angels, Spirits, of all degrees, with every thing that has Being in the Viſible and Inviſible parts of the World.</p>
                  <p>And as their moſt Emphatical Argument, in reverence to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Original, they plead the Text of Scripture, where it is ſaid, <hi>That God form'd Man out of Clay,</hi> as precedent Matter.</p>
                  <p>But this excludes not the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of that Clay ſo wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:95951:28"/>Impreſs'd by the Almighty as to compleat the Figure of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity; unleſs they annex per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity to Matter, which were to double Eternity, by aſſigning that Infinite Attribute no leſs to Matter then God: An abſurdity condemn'd by the Doctrine of the <hi>Theiſt,</hi> as already Inſtanc'd; who rather beholds the Univerſe as the Object of his Admiration, then undertakes to aſſert by any Method, that he can contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate, the Manner of its wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Exiſtence; as not poſſible, in his Judgment, to conceive how any thing had precedent Being that is not manifeſt in a preſent Cauſe. Inſomuch that he doubts not to affirm that had Man been capable of apprehending how the World, with all the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars it contains, was produc'd,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:95951:29"/>there had not been wanted the Inſcriptions of Providence, on whatſoever has Being, within its Circumference, whereby Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind might have legibly diſcern'd how its total and Parts had the compleat Structures, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtences that are viſible to the Eye.</p>
                  <p>But ſince the whole with its wonderful Particulars are within the Complex of a mighty Round more amazingly vaſt then can be Intelligently penetrated by humane Senſe, or the height of its Diameter meaſur'd by any Scale of Thoughts that can A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to the utmoſt Point of its ſupream Cauſe: By the muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Omnipotent we are in ſome ſort familiarly acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with miraculous Objects tho not with their miraculous Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:95951:29"/>And notwithſtanding that ſpiritual Eſſences together with their admir'd Proprieties, are not ſo readily defin'd, or the manner of their Exiſtence and Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as Corporeal Beings, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever wonderful, that actually Imploy the Senſe as they ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathize in bodily Temperaments, Parts, or Proportions, with thoſe of Mankind: Yet even of theſe we may have ſuch real apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as admirably Approximate the, otherwiſe, remote ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or their Order, Conduct, and Nature. Let the Example be taken from the Sun, and Stars, which the <hi>Theiſt</hi> rather deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates ſpiritual Appearances, or equivalently ſuch, then any other definition, given of them, by the greateſt Philoſopher; and he may be well allowed that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:95951:30"/>if he proves them equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in their refin'd Illuminations, Beings, and Motions, to ſuch ſtupendious Excellencies that can be no otherwiſe comprehended then as they are effecatiouſly ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual.</p>
                  <p>The Grand Philoſopher <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> (as before quoted,) by the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteneſs of his Intellect, gives the Definition of quinteſſential Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the Celeſtial Lumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which ſignifies a Fifth diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Eſſence from any thing that had any Ingredients of the Four Elements. But had he as accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately conſider'd their wonderful Motions and Celerity, as they conſummate their Revolutions, he might have allow'd them the Epithites of ſpiritual Equivalents, in every reſpect.</p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:95951:30"/>
                  <p>The beſt Account that the moſt celebrated Aſtronomers can give of the Suns diurnal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, is that he exceeds fifteen Millions of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miles in the four and twenty Hours; and conſequently, that in one Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute of Time his expedition is ſomewhat more then eleven Thouſand a Hundred and eleven Miles of the ſame Account: Which incomprehenſible ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſeems liker to vaniſhing then apparent Motion. It being Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for any thing that has bodily Compoſition to move with that Celirity, becauſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever has Corporeal Parts muſt take up ſpace, and therefore move by ſlower Degrees and Computations then in the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple given of the Suns accelerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Nor is there any Individual
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:95951:31"/>Motion, within the Circle of the Univerſe, below the Orbs above, that has any competent Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to their admirable Move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The haſty Currents of the Ocean, or wings of the lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Winds are ſlow, in their utmoſt Expiditions, and ſo are the moſt ſudden flaſhes of Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; if compar'd with one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Journey of the Celeſtial Spheres,</p>
                  <p>And what is of higher Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, were it ſo decreed by Providence, 'tis as poſſible for the Sun to finiſh his diurnal Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in the ſame Minute of Time, that the Aſtronomers al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot to the Miles above mention'd, as for a Thought, that is ſpirited by the Soul, to Imagine, in a moment, a Methematical Line extended from the Eaſt point
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:95951:31"/>to the Weſt of the Horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon.</p>
                  <p>And thus may the wondrous Acceleration of the Sun be no leſs preſpicuouſly contemplated, then, in a Inſtant, may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd any Ray of his arrive to the Eye.</p>
                  <p>But ſhould any ſolid Body, whether little or great, be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to move, with the ſwifteſt Imagination, from any one Point of the Compaſs to another; its dimenſions of Length, Breadth, and Height, both in a Phiſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and Mathematical Senſe, would have local removes, or tranſition from place to place by ſuch parts of Time as can have no comparative Proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Inſtance already given, of the Suns momentary Celerity, then 'tis poſſible to parallel the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:95951:32"/>ſtart of a Thought to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of bodily Motion.</p>
                  <p>From whence it follows, that if the diurnal Revolution of the Sun is in every particle of Time, miraculous; a more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary definition ought to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to his Revolution and Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. No one viſible Radiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sun but reſembles, as the learned in Opticks deliver, a Geometrical Line: But becauſe no ſuch Line can be the Object of Sight, but as it ſeems to have Corporal Breadth: It has theſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pleas'd Divine Providence ſo comfortably to Illuminate the World, that every Beam tranſmitted by the Sun, is viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with his Figure, tho his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence be not more underſtood, by any definitive Term, then the Miracle of his Light and Motion.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:95951:32"/>
                  <p>On which ground, the <hi>Theiſt</hi> conceives it very ſignificant to attribute, inſtead of other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination, the Equivalency of ſpiritual appearances to the Sun and Stars, as ſuitable to undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Proprieties in them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is apprehended that ſpiritual Exiſtencies may be ſeen, tho not underſtood; yet by their Viſibility directed, as the ſhining guides of Providence, to Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine more excellent Beings in the Supream Palace of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
                  <p>Next to the Immenſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of the Stars and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitary Orbs that compleat the Twenty-four hourly Periods of the Day: The <hi>Theiſt</hi> fully admites the ſudain diverſity of their Longitudes, Latitudes, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centricities, Oppoſitions Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:95951:33"/>direct, or Retrograde, together with their various Heights and Diſtances from the Centre of the Earths ſuperficies: To demonſtrate all which, would require a large Aſtronomical Syſtem.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore the <hi>Theiſt</hi> annexeth to the diurnal, his additional Wonder to what may be uſually inferr'd from obſervation of the Suns Annual Motion, by which the vaſt Orb of Light, and the Worlds miraculous Eye, beholds its Brightneſs forward and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward remov'd, ſwifter then can be Inſtanc'd by Thought, yet with no contradiction to Time; tho without the Suns contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory Motion neithcr the hours of the Day or Year could be number'd: If by his glorious diurnal progreſs he ſumms Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:95951:33"/>of Degrees forward, he moves, in the ſame Compaſs of Time, ſomewhat leſs then one Degree backward towards the gradual finiſhing of thc Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Year: In which, as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny periodical Bleſſings of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, the Elementary Round of the Univerſe has preſervation, as alſo the Life, Growth, and Subſiſtence of its Innumerable Individuals. From whence the <hi>Theiſt</hi> has reiterated aſſurance that the Sun and Stars, as to their undefinable Eſſence and Motion, may be term'd, (as before Inſerted,) ſpiritual Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valents; ſince no Corporeal Movement can poſſibly perform, in all its Parts, too contrary Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the ſame Inſtant of Time.</p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:95951:34"/>
                  <p>But whatſoever may be ſaid to have a ſpiritual Operation, cannot be circumſcrib'd by place, or in the Phraſe of the Schools, have the Epithite of <hi>prius</hi> and <hi>poſterius</hi> in Motion; wherefore the Miracle, not otherwiſe to be worded, may be, in ſome kind compar'd to the expanſion, this way, and that way, of a Thought, or as one may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, as precedently mention'd, a Geometrical Line extended, to any diſtance, forward and backward by the ſwiftneſs of Imagination. And whoſoever would oppoſe the definition here given, as it relates to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Beings above, the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt</hi> leaves him, to the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of his Brain, to find a better.</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:95951:34"/>
                  <p>In the mean while, 'tis very manifeſt, that by no Speculation of theirs they can give any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Definition, whereby they might ſignificantly extricate the difficulties, they are under, by endeavouring to compute the wonderful Motions above other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then as they allow Corporeal Subſtances to the Sun and Stars: Which tho miraculouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing Effectually ſuch, becauſe otherwiſe Men and Creatures could not have the benefit of their Illuminations, Heat, and Influence: Yet, (for the Reaſons already given,) the <hi>Theiſt</hi> affirms that as in their Motions, and Operations, they are virtually ſpiritual, or which is all one with the Denomination, (before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſerted,) of ſpiritual Equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents: Notwithſtanding, that for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:95951:35"/>the advantage of humane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception and Commodities of Life, they ſeem to be corpore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally diſcernable. And no Man can affirm that the Omnipotent diſpoſer of the Univerſe, with all its appurtenances, could not, by miraculous Benevolence, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr bodily appearance on Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtencies that, conſider'd in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, were diſtitute of Viſible Beings.</p>
                  <p>But ſince the Motions of the Celeſtial Orbs muſt evidently relate to their Manner of Exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Eſſence, the <hi>Theiſt</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes to demonſtrate the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion from the moſt Erudite and accurate Aſtronomical Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtems.</p>
                  <p>Let the <hi>Copernican Hypotheſis,</hi> becauſe in this Age, of greateſt Repute, be made the Example;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:95951:35"/>by which 'tis alledg'd, as the moſt facile proof, that the Sun ſtands as the looker on, in his Sphere, whilſt the Earth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms the diurnal and annual Revolution, which <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> and <hi>Tycho,</hi> with other learned Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervators, Attributed to the Sun: Tho it be well known that <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernicus</hi> deriv'd his <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> from Antient <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> who, Imagin'd the Earth to be a Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net betwixt <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> and ſome of his Succeſſors.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding, it muſt be granted that the Ingenuity of <hi>Copernicus</hi> added ſome Refine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Tenent of the Earths Motion: Yet rather taken up by him, as he apprehended it more aptly Coherent with Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical computations then really his belief: As appears by the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:95951:36"/>Dedication of his Works to an Eminent Cardinal.</p>
                  <p>The Figure deſcrib'd by the Earth, in her diurnal and annual Revolution, was circular, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Copernicus:</hi> And herein, except in his <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> he differ'd neither from <hi>Ptolomy</hi> or <hi>Tycho,</hi> as they determin'd to the Sun and Stars circular Motions, but <hi>Kepler,</hi> who liv'd after the lateſt of theſe, appropriated to the Earth an Elipſical Revolution, whence he Imply'd that the Earth is of the Shape of an Elip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis: Which if true of the Earths Figure, the ſame might be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to be deſcrib'd by her Motion; becauſe no Corporeal Subſtance can move, but it muſt neceſſarily aſſimulate its out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Form and Proportion: So if a Roler be turn'd on the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:95951:36"/>Ground it will Impreſs, if there diſcernable, its figurative Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation; beſides abundance of Examples that might be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>But as for the Incommenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable boundary of the Univerſe, 'tis doubtleſs circular becauſe the moſt perfect of Figures: In which there is no point of its Beginning or End, if conſider'd in its ſelf; and therefore by its admirable Propriety more ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly circumſcrib'd the World with all the Wonders compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in it.</p>
                  <p>How the Earth, if ſuppoſs'd to move can, in its total Complex, be properly term'd either Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolouſy round, as <hi>Copernicus</hi> Syſtematically allow'd, or a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical ſolid, in the Form of an Elipſis, as moſt of the late <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernicans</hi>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:95951:37"/>Imagine; Is far from being Corobarated by any ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Demonſtration? But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, on the contrary, occular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confuted by viewing of the different Scituations in the Earth of Hills, Mountains, Valleys, Rocks, Woods, Seas, Rivers, and the like: Which cannot, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently be circumſcrib'd by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Figure that can be nam'd Geometrically Regular.</p>
                  <p>And if granted, that the Earth does move, in any method they delineate, they produce no proof that it viſibly does ſo: Inſtead of which they undertake to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that it may have the Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they aſſign to it, inſtead of the Sun, and not be ſeen to move, according to the noted Verfe in <hi>Virgil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:95951:37"/>
                  <q>—Provehimur portu, teraſque urbeſque Recedunt.</q>
                  <p>Yet this is their firmed Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereby they would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade opinon, that the Eye is not ſo certain, in beholding the riſing and ſetting of the Orbs above, as their Doctrine.</p>
                  <p>The main Allegation by which they ſeem not only to warrant the Earths Motion, in all Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities, Inſtead of the Sun; but alſo to deny diurnal Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, both to the fix'd Stars and Planets, as they only appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate to the Motion of the Earth, the twenty four Hours that ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate the natural Day; is, that if diurnal Circulation he granted to the ſupream Sphere of Stars, they muſt expedite, according to Aſtronomical computation,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:95951:38"/>643000 <hi>German</hi> Miles in a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or two Seconds of an Hour: As alſo that the Planet <hi>Saturn</hi> next to them, in the vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Orb and Height, muſt Revolve 909 of thoſe Miles by the ſame Meaſure and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of Time. All which may be granted, tho confeſſedly won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful, if allowed to the Stars, as before deſcrib'd, Motion and Eſſence equivalently ſpiritual, that like the tranſition of a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Thought, ſpirited by the Soul, may ſurpaſs any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, or meaſure of Miles that can be computed, as has been precedently Inſtanc'd, and would tend to unneceſſary Repetition if again mention'd.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore, ſhould any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecter of this Treatiſe ſhock at the Epithite of ſpiritual Equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:95951:38"/>attributed to the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Expedition of the Celeſtial Luminaries; he ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that Words devis'd, where the Subject treated on is not in it ſelf exactly Intelligible, may have the requiſits of a Definition, if thereby probably open'd to the underſtanding, of whatſoever had been more obſcure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it.</p>
                  <p>Nor can the Importancy of the Authors ſuppoſition, on this ſublime Account, be farther tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able then Aſtronomical <hi>Pheno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menas</hi> Antient or Modern, if with die likeneſs of proof, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by them, they compute, in order to reduce within the Compaſs of Imaginary Rules, what had elſe been too bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs for humane Science.</p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:95951:39"/>
                  <p>'Tis not to be doubted that the <hi>Copernicans</hi> will be oppoſers of the manner of the Syſtem, deliver'd here relating to the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and Motions of the Stars of every Denomination, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that the groſly conceive that they are of a Corporeal Nature as well as the Earth, which they have Elevated into the room of a Planet betwixt the Sphere of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> according to the Tenents of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> (as before obſerv'd:) For which they give no better account then that the Body of the Earth, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted by Aſtronomers, at leaſt, a Hundred and ſixty ſix times leſſer then the appearing dimenſions of the Sun, may ſooner Revolve a eleven Thouſand one Hundred and eleven of our Miles in a Minute, then the Greater Body,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:95951:39"/>as they call it, of the Sun: The hard to apprehend how either of them, in a Corporeal Senſe, can expedite that Celerity in the ſame Portion of Time: For the Earth however diminutive, if compar'd with the Sun, yet as to common Underſtanding, and the Meaſure that is allow'd its Compaſs, it ſeems too big in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Figure, to Anſwer the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents of the <hi>Copernicans</hi> by the ſwiftneſs of its Progreſſion in a temporary Period ſo very ſmall. And as they cannot but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Movement wonderful, whether allotted to the Sun or Earth, ſo it may be undeniably a-like, in either of them; if proceeding from a miraculous Cauſe.</p>
                  <p>Nor does it appear, if gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Theorem of the Earths
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:95951:40"/>Motion, that either <hi>Copernicus,</hi> or the moſt diligent of his Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomical Succeſſors, have by any exactneſs in their Computations, exceeded ſuch as have been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd by the <hi>Ptolomaick</hi> or or <hi>Tyconique</hi> Method; the latter of which perſons ſtands at this Day, more renown'd for his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate Obſervations, than any, that can be for any other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, if compar'd with his.</p>
                  <p>But becauſe Demonſtration is a ſurer proof then tan be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd from the greateſt Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of Argument: Let it be granted that the Sun as well as the Earth, has bodily Parts, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Copernican</hi> Senſe, and <hi>Hypotheſis;</hi> as alſo that the Sun is the Center of of the Earth: Or that the Earth, as others af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, is the Center of the Sun:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:95951:40"/>And let both of them in Figure, be acknowledg'd Circular.</p>
                  <p>By the Diagram, here annex'd, 'will be manifeſt, that if both of them be ſuppoſs'd at once to move, ſuitable to the Syſtems, here mention'd, of both Parties, 'twill be evident that in any Period of Time they will equally finiſh one Revolution.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore in this Diagram, let A, B, M, C, D, Repreſent the diurnal Orb of the Sun; And let E, F, G, H, be the ſuppoſs'd diurnal Orb of the Earth, and S be the common Center of both their Orbs; 'Twill be found by certain Proportion, that in the ſame Compaſs of Time, however vaſt the ſpace that the Earth can be Imagin'd to move from F, to N, in the ſame
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:95951:41"/>Time the much greater Orb of, the Sun may Revolve from B to M.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>the Sun's orbit</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Demonſtration in Words are thus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In Parallel Circles, as the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midiameter of one, is to the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:95951:41"/>Semidiameter of the other, ſo is ſine, vers'd ſine, ſubtenſe of one Circle, to the right ſine, vers'd ſine, ſubtenſe of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: According to the 11 <hi>Prop.</hi> of the 7 Book of <hi>Euclid,</hi> and confirm'd by the 4 of the 6, for as S F : F P ⸬ S B : B K: the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angles S P F and S K B are Equiangled, the Angle a S com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to both, and right Angled at P and K, and therefore the third equal in both, as alſo the ſides proportional: The ſame is demonſtrable of either of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Triangles.</p>
                  <p>To make all which evident to Senſe, let a ſmall Thread be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten'd or held in the Center S; and move the other end of it from B to M, it ſhall as ſoon come to the greater ſpace B M,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:95951:42"/>as to the leſſer F N, which was to be prov'd; and the ſame may be Affirm'd of F G, in in the Triangle S, F, G, or of B C, in the greateſt Triangle S, B, C. Wherefore the Sun may as ſoon Revolve from B, to M, as the Earth can from F, to N, if both be granted to move, at once by the ſame Cauſe: And what can be appli'd to both, if ſuppoſs'd to be mov'd togteher, ought to be ſeparately allow'd the Sun as more ſuitable to oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Evidence.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore the <hi>Theiſt</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluds, this ſecond Head of this Treatiſe, with demonſtrative aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance that the <hi>Copernicans</hi> are no leſs Confuted as they would Imagine that the Earth moves, Inſtead of the Sun, then they, or
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:95951:42"/>any other oppoſers muſt be, if controdictory to any of his former Principles rationally aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="particular">
                  <head>The <hi>Third</hi> Particular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicating the <hi>Faith</hi> of the <hi>Theiſt,</hi> and his Manner of Adoration, redounding from thence.</head>
                  <p>TIS not doubted by the <hi>Theiſt</hi> that it has been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough prov'd in the beginning of this Treatiſe, that the open Cauſe and Effects of Divine Providence ſenſibly beheld in the ordain'd Conſtitution of the Univerſe, and all its Parts, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o many undeniable publicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:95951:43"/>that ought to Convict the Reverence of the humane Soul, in Reference to the Worſhip of Omnipotency; could by no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means then by micaculous Order and viſible Deeds, be ſo familiarly communicated to the preception of Mankind; all which has been precedently Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd.</p>
                  <p>And whoſoever denies that holy Belief, may not, in that Method, be perſpicuouſly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erted, muſt have recourſe to ſuch Relations of Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip as cannot, in their Nature, exceed moral Certainties, or the Effects of Cuſtome and Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion; which, in their utmoſt extent, have leſs aſſurance the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is evident in the Proof of any one Propoſition of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Euclide:</hi> And 'twer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:95951:43"/>abſur'd to imagine that a Man ſhould be more able to explain the Properties of a Line, or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficies, then to Demonſtrate how he comes by that main Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, of his Creed, the belief of one God.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore the <hi>Theiſt,</hi> as an Infallible Motive to the duty of his Faith, has ſuperlative aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance conſpieuouſly aſſerted in the miraculous Conduct, Facts, and Munificence of the Almighty, without the help of Man as his ſubordinate Tutor; otherwiſe then as it is Imcum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent on the more aſſiduous di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcernments of ſome to remind others of the pious tegard they ought to have to Works of the Almighty, ſo manifeſt to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Eye.</p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:95951:44"/>
                  <p>Whereas, other perſwaſions, together with their undiſcerna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble motives, or ſuppoſitious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins, convey'd, and impos'd by the Intereſted diverſities of humane Allowance, make their obſcure Entrance into the Soul of the believer, and by their fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented oppositions inſtigate po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemick Diſputes with ſuch dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Animoſities as patroniſe War and Deſtruction, whereby they may juſtly be deem'd, inſtead of Religions, the Incendiaries of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and blood: Which ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine Impieties, or deſtroying of Lives on the account of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted or uncertain Tenents; are wholly avoided by the Principles of the <hi>Theiſt,</hi> no leſs Impoſſible to be oppos'd then if Men ſhould deny the Being of the miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous World they Inhabit, or the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:95951:44"/>Gifts of Providence which they have Eyes to behold.</p>
                  <p>But the <hi>Theiſt</hi> is not deſirous farther to enlarge or apply, what might be ſaid on this occaſion, leaſt he ſhould provoke Men of words, or ſuch that with more Paſſion then Senſe, would be his wrangling oppoſers.</p>
                  <p>If he Affirms that the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe is the mediate Object of his devotion to the Omnipotent; he does not therefore conclude that the World was produc'd or Man in it, as if any glory, by either, or both, could be added to God, who is Eternally glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in himſelf; and not at all by conſtituting, in a direct Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, the ſpecies of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, ſo wickedly temper'd and compos'd in Body and Mind;
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:95951:45"/>and with that generality too, that the Rolls of the Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous are numberleſs, in every conſideration, if compar'd with the few good: Inſomuch, that ſome have attributed the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of Man to an accidental aberration of Nature, in the Courſe of her Works; or her Ambition, by that Enormity, to raiſe humane. Individuals that ſhould be wickedly predominant over themſelves and the reſt of her Creatures: Wherefore they conclude that Mankind had as corrupt a beginning as 'tis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd in too many notorious Examples of Life and Death: As alſo that they could not be Creatures allow'd by the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to preſent him with the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs of their praiſe or Prayer.</p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:95951:45"/>
                  <p>To which the <hi>Theiſt</hi> Replys, that it cannot be denied that the vaſt Troops of the Wicked abundantly over-number the Good; Notwithſtanding, their facinourous Deeds aboliſh not the rational Capacities they have to amend, or to be inform'd by the diſcreet Integrity of the better principled few: So that 'tis either for want of diligent Inſtructors, or as they are not incourag'd, as they ought to be, in applying their aſſiduity to impreſs Divine Moralities; whereby multitudes might be render'd more propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly devout; and therefore not meerly the natural Inclinations and Tempers of Men that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth their averſneſs from Piety and Obedience.</p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:95951:46"/>
                  <p>And till Rulers of People are leſs blemiſh'd by their Principles and Actions, and more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous Examples of eminent Goodneſs to ſuch they govern, there will be but ſmall progreſs towards a general Redreſs: By reaſon that where Men can be beneficially countenanced in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bad, they will ſeldom Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, by their worldly loſs, to the benefit of their Souls.</p>
                  <p>In fine, ſhould a Man, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the laſt Inſtance, think himſelf beholding to his blind expreſſion of Nature for all; or what is more, be ſo ungratiouſly thoughtleſs as in no manner of notion to be thankfully accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for his Being, or the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of Life enjoy'd by him: 'Tis very probable that ſuch a perſon, if mention'd to him, that it
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:95951:46"/>muſt be ſome beneign Cauſe that had given him his Intellectual faculties above other Animals, and likewiſe capacities of Mind to ſubjugate them, in divers kinds, for his uſe and ſubſiſtance, would acknowledge, by ſome Denomination or Method, that he ought to give thanks, as well as pray that the Commodities of Life might be continu'd to him here, tho he believ'd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of a future World: And therefore deteſtable Inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateneſs in ſuch as appear neither Proſelites to Reaſon, or Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
                  <p>Others there are, and of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute perception, that want no diligence in obſerving the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Conduct and Order diffuſs'd throughout the Univerſe and all its Particulars: Who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:95951:47"/>their utmoſt endeavour, are at a ſtand, becauſe they Judge that they cannot diſcern in the open face of Providence other then the univerſality of tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry living and dying, with their appurtenancies, as they relate to every Individual of Life: And therefore conclude that Mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is the total end of Mankind; there being nothing, as they conceive, in any method of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, that gives any aſſurance of ſurviving after Death, or appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Being of Immortality.</p>
                  <p>But Men, of this genius, whilſt they imploy the inquiſitive ſubtilities of their Brain below themſelves, omit the Judgment they might receive from their Eyes in taking their proſpect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; by which they might viſibly apprehend that the Skies
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:95951:47"/>are adorn'd with numberleſs Stars, that by no humane obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation had ever any alteration, or periods Incident to diſſolution: And therefore ſo many admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Emblems of the Immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that has Being in them; as by the Eſſential proprieties of their Nature, Figure, Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and Motion, is very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt; and it has been pertinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prov'd, in the ſecond Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of this Treatiſe, that a Thought of the Mind can reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by ſuddain expedition, the ſwifteſt Acceleration of a Star: And may not therefore the Soul of Man, from whence ſuch Thought proceeds, be as Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal as the brighteſt of the Orbs above.</p>
                  <p>And thus may be encourag'd the ſublime Hope that Mankind
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:95951:48"/>ought to have of endleſs Life and Perfection; ſince by the Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the Almighty there is Immortality beheld in the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries of Day and Night: And why the humane Soul ſhould not be granted as capable of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting ſubſiſtence is not to be diſprov'd?</p>
                  <p>Too many there are, that by their infamous Converſation and Lives are ſo far from me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riting a mention in the refin'd Liſt of Immortality, as they deſerve not to enjoy the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon benefits of worldly Life: Whilſt in Soul they poſſeſs ſo uncomfortable a Being, that by Reaſon of their Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, 'tis their utmoſt wiſh that Mortality may be their Period. Wherefore they Judge that 'tis no Intereſt to their Lives to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:95951:48"/>pray, unleſs their ſupplications might be admitted, whereby they would be exempted from Death, and continu'd as bad as they are; and ſo they are here left to themſelves, till they think fit to be better.</p>
                  <p>And now to conclude with the Method of the <hi>Theiſt</hi>'s De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, to which he conceives he has ſo many palpable motives from the bounties of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to the Life he poſſeſſeth, and whatſoever tends to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in Body and Mind, that he were guilty, of a ſloathful Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſhould he not acknowledge his thankfulneſs with his daily Bread; and the more, becauſe frequently beſtow'd by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of providence.</p>
                  <p>As to his manner of Prayer, the <hi>Theiſt</hi> affirms it inſeparably
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:95951:49"/>annexed to the Entireneſs of his Belief and Method of Devotion; which he conceives cannot have a more refin'd Evidence, than that it perfectly avoids all diſputable Commixture or Impurity from any Notions of Erronius Faith or their Parcels of Belief complica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or intermix'd with the diffus'd Creeds of ſome others: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he conſiders his Perſuaſion as an infallible Purity, or refin'd Nature of Belief, abſolutely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commitant with the Worſhip of one God, palpably Reveal'd in the ſtupendious Being of his Works, and the Conduct of Providence viſible in them; on which account, it is impoſſible to add, to ſo many Superlative Convictions of the Soul, any particular Article of Faith, that is leſs manifeſt than the Miracles
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:95951:49"/>of Omnipotency perſpicuouſly diſpers'd throughout the total Fabrick of the Univerſe, as it comprehends the Wonders be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held above and below.</p>
                  <p>And as Divine Admiration muſt neceſſarily produce Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from the humane Soul; 'tis no leſs undeniably conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, that an Eternal Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by actual Wonders, is a Motive above all others, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is Effected the Piety of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion confirm'd by the bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac'd Miracles of the World, and its Univerſal Providence: On which <hi>Baſis,</hi> by the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Theiſt,</hi> does conſiſt the common Place of his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as has been precedently Inſtanc'd.</p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:95951:50"/>
                  <p>If other Devotions have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larg'd their Creeds beyond open Miracles, or as they were, in Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ſo many providential Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals of Worſhip Univerſally Evident from the time that Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind had Being in the World, the Progreſſion of ſuch Beliefs could have no other Riſe then as they were ſuppos'd to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd to particular Perſons: And were more or leſs valu'd, by Men that duely conſider'd the original Start, or Comencement of different Perſuaſions, as the Authors, or firſt Propagaters of them, were renown'd for extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Prudence, Moralities of Life, and holy Converſation: Or ſignally Celebrated for mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Deeds conceiv'd to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd by them; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by Education and Cuſtome
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:95951:50"/>deſcended, ſo reputed, to Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
                  <p>Inumerable Examples might be given, of this kind, from undoubted Stories of Ages paſt; but none more remarkably An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, or of longer continuance then the groſs, or horrible Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, that Worſhipt the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty in the Perſons of Men; or, like to an Arithmetical Fracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ½, divided Godſhip by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it Infus'd into humane Body.</p>
                  <p>And thus did not a few of the Antients who attributed to he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Perſons, and famous Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of pious Inſtitutions and Precepts, the Titles of Demy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gods: Not as they believ'd them ſuch, but as their Signal Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:95951:51"/>and Sacred Ordinations, could not have ſufficient Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation without a ſublime Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thite: And the more pardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in thoſe Authors, becauſe no better meanes was known to them whereby Mankind might be indued to Holy Obedience and the Sacred Duty that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to civil Society and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>But as the Intention might be, in ſome reſpects, pardonable, the Conſequence was highly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious to the Devotion and Peace of Men; as one fellow or other, in ſeveral Ages of the World preſum'd to be Inſpir'd with Celeſtial Dictates: Or for more ſupreme Confirmation of his Doctrine attributed Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to himſelf; when he obſerv'd
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:95951:51"/>that Men were credulous enough to believe him.</p>
                  <p>But theſe could ſignifie no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: then ſo many contriv'd Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtorages, and were by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, accordingly diſcover'd, as may be obſerv'd from Stories, with which the <hi>Theiſt</hi> does, in no kind, intermix Chriſtianity; notwithſtanding it has not that dateleſs Evidence, as to that Denomination, with his own: It being undeniable that the Belief of one God was a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Motive that had its O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal with the Being of the World, and therefore prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to all ſubſequent Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships.</p>
                  <p>But ſince the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity was deliver'd by the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:95951:52"/>Preaching and Writings of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Perſons, who by the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of their Lives and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation could have no ſuch Indirect Ends and Intereſts that might derogate from the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, conceiv'd by them, of whatſoever they Atteſted: The <hi>Theiſt</hi> does, no ways, detract from the Goodneſs of their Doctrine; and the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it has an agreeable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency with the manifeſt Text of Devine Providence.</p>
                  <p>For 'tis a Devine Chriſtian Moral, unparallel'd by other Perſuaſions, that good Deeds are to be done, for the ſake of Good, notwithſtanding the unworthineſs of the Receiver: So by the Conduct of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence its Munificence is viſibly
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:95951:52"/>diffus'd to all Stations of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, however deſertleſly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd and injoy'd by them.</p>
                  <p>The Conſideration of which, together with the pious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, Reſignations in Spirit, and contempt of worldly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, Eminent in, not a few, Chriſtian Profeſſors, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth no ſmall deſire, in the <hi>Theiſt,</hi> that he might Aſſociate with them in ſaying Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and moſt merciful Father: And conſequently that in his Judgment, next to the Belief of one God, Chriſtian Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ought to be Embrac'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any other in the World.</p>
                  <p>And thus you have a Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary of the moſt pertinent Science, and Tenents applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:95951:53"/>to the Doctrine of <hi>Theiſme,</hi> not hitherto devulg'd, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo its Tendency to the Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Holy Religion and Practice.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:95951:53"/>
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>THE main Intention of this Treatiſe has, like the Figure of <hi>Janus,</hi> two Faces: By the one, of which, the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may take a backward proſpect of ſuch prophane Superſtitions and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips as were frequent in the Traditions and Writings of the Antients; ſome of which are particularly mention'd in this Book: Together with others, better known, then readily number'd; yet ſo diſplay'd that their Errors and Abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are totally render'd Inconſiſtent with the ſuperlative Conviction which the Providence of the Almighty has viſibly convey'd to Humane Underſtanding.</p>
               <p>But ſuch has been the groſs Neglect, or Supidity in Men, that they have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly applyed the Devotion of their Souls, rather to the artful Inſinuations of Counterfeit Tenents, then to the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:95951:54"/>and palpable acknowledgment that there is Deity from what every com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Eye may diſcern in the vaſt Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre of his Works that contains Innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Scenes of manifeſt Wonders that could have no other Author then one Omnipotent.</p>
               <p>The other ſignal Part, if not the moſt uſeful, was ſo to introduce Atheiſme on the publick Stage, that it might have a reproachful and full defeat from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of a God, by the Doctrine of the <hi>Theiſt;</hi> no leſs proſpicuouſly diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable then that Mankind, with what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is beſides in the Compaſs of the Univerſe, are, by Divine appointment, under a miraculous Conduct.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding however powerful thoſe Motives, the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> to cover his ſupine diſregard of all ſuch conſpicuous and ſublime Evidences that ought to be undeniably Attributed to the Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Management, and Power of a dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Author, ſeems to acquieſce in what he terms Nature; and to which obſcure Denomination he endeavours to annex the total ſum of his Infidelity, by urging that whatſoever has Being above, or below, have an ordinary and natural
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:95951:54"/>Subſiſtency from the Method of Cauſes and Effects.</p>
               <p>Tho he cannot deny that, by ſo affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, he is enforc'd to grant that this Empreſs of the Univerſe, which he calls Nature, is not Intellegible by any ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Definition of the Word, or any Proprieties he Attributes to her; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not poſſible for him to give any original Account either of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Being of Man, Animal, or Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: Or when the Sun and Stars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan firſt to ſhine, for Univerſal Benefit; no more then he is certainly able to tell what a Clock 'twas before he was born.</p>
               <p>Too many there are that, if but En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd with Tales of Magick, Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, or the devices and feats of a Jugler, tho a deſpicable Impoſter, will not only incline to believe them, but heartily wiſh they might behold ſuch Imaginary Facts perform'd, which but related they deem ſupernatural Wonders.</p>
               <p>But were the ſame Perſons Interoga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whether, by any of their Senſes, they as eaſily were charm'd by the miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Conſtitution of the Univerſe and all it Circumſcribs, 'tis to be doubted
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:95951:55"/>that not a few of them would with the common <hi>Atheiſt</hi> reply, that although divers Exiſtencies and Operations, in the World they behold, appear ſtupendiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wonderful, yet, as they conſider them as things of Courſe, they could not Judge them ſo extraordinary as the Miracles they had heard of, but for ought they could prove, were never perform'd; which Imbecillities, in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Comprehenſion, proceed from no other Fond then want of Judicious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, or not being pertinently In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by Superiors.</p>
               <p>Should it be demanded, by the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, why Texts of Holy Scripture, or Arguments from Venerable Writers have not been more frequently Cited then are to be found in the precedent Book; the Anſwer, that can moſt properly be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, is, that the Authors deſign was barely to Convict the <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> by proofs Inſerted, whereby the open Evidence of <hi>Theiſme,</hi> in the Belief of one God, without other Divine Teſtimonial, or Article of Faith, might be aſcertain'd to the cleareſt Eye of the Intellect: Not but all neceſſary Texts, of Holy Writ, are thereby effectually Imply'd, as is
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:95951:55"/>no leſs perſpicuouſly diſcernable from the demonſtrative Parts of this Treatiſe, then if pronounc'd with the Pſalmiſt. <hi>That the Heavens declare the glory of God, and the Firmament ſheweth his han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor can the <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> if not obdurate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch, be by any other proceſs ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Convicted: As he that may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably extend his Faith to the Belief of an Infinite Power and Being, from Actual and Viſible Miracles that could be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd no otherwiſe then by an Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Author, Will not ſo eaſily devote his Aſſent to the moſt celebrated Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of any Writing, however Divine it ought to be underſtood.</p>
               <p>'Tis reported of the Philoſopher <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> tho far different in Opinion from the obſtinacy of the Antient, or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> that he having perus'd the Books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> his Judgment of them was that they had in them the voice of God, tho otherwiſe nothing was prov'd by them: But had that great Man of Science throughly conſider'd what might have been affirm'd ſuitable to what is ſufficiently Demonſtrated in this Work;
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:95951:56"/>he would have at leaſt declar'd for the Doctrine of <hi>Theiſme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſuch is the inveterate Impudence and <hi>Odium</hi> that too many, in our days, have againſt Holy Belief, of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Denomination, that it is their Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury to cabal for <hi>Atheiſme</hi> and <hi>Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> as they mingle thoſe Impieties with their Wine and Mirth; by which they would aſcribe to themſelves the Title of Wits, however wickedly Principled, or ſo fooliſhly Impious that they reſiſt the Dictates of Senſe: As if they had Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvedly confin'd their Souls to ſuch a narrowneſs of Conception that the broadeſt Miracles of Divine Providence were not to operate on their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings.</p>
               <p>But 'tis hop'd, if they ſhall pleaſe, with any reaſonable diſcretion, to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the Subſtance of this Book, that there Infidility, together with their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucheries of Life, will be ſo far Reform'd as that they will approve themſelves bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Subjects, in their Duties to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, then hitherto they have been.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:95951:56"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
